<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anatomie of Pope Ioane Wherein her life, manners and death is liuely layed abroad and opened, and the forged cauils and allegations that our aduersaries vse further, thoroughly vnripped and confuted. Necessarie for all those that are not fully acquainted with the storie, and not vnfruitfull to all them that loue and embrace the true religion of Christ, and abhorre the sortish illusions of Romish antichrist. Written by I.M.</title>
            <author>Mayo, John, fl. 1607-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849455</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1523:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anatomie of Pope Ioane Wherein her life, manners and death is liuely layed abroad and opened, and the forged cauils and allegations that our aduersaries vse further, thoroughly vnripped and confuted. Necessarie for all those that are not fully acquainted with the storie, and not vnfruitfull to all them that loue and embrace the true religion of Christ, and abhorre the sortish illusions of Romish antichrist. Written by I.M.</title>
                  <author>Mayo, John, fl. 1607-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Field dwelling in great Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.M. = John Mayo.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device on title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B³.</note>
                  <note>Pages cropped and stained, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joan (Legendary Pope) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANATOMIE OF POPE IOANE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN HER LIFE, MAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and death is liuely layed abroad and opened, and the forged cauils and allegations that our aduerſaries vſe for her, throughly vnrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and confuted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neceſſarie for all thoſe that are not fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ſtorie, and not vnfruitfull to all them that loue and embrace the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of Chriſt, and abhorre the ſottiſh illuſions of Romiſh Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by I. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Field dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in great Woodſtreet. 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14603:2"/>
            <head>To the reaſonable Reader.</head>
            <p>THou haſt here mine Anatomie of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> briefly compriſed: if not cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as it ought, blame mine inſufficiencie: if not as an expert Chirurgion, impute the fault to want of skill, and not of good will. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, <hi>errare fortaſſis poſſim, hareticus eſſe non poſſum.</hi> The matter hereof is ſo manifeſt, that <hi>corun copiae</hi> were needleſſe to poliſh it, and the truth ſo euident, that the Pumi-ſtone of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and ſuperficiall eloquence would not haue bene requiſite to flouriſh and ſmooth it. Reade therefore willingly, iudge indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, and correct friendly. Let reaſon rule thee, authoritie moue thee, and truth enforce thee. And let vs both pray together, that the truth may be maintained, all errors confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and Gods name glorified. Fare-well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:14603:2"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. How our aduerſaries the Papiſts are aſhamed of Pope Ioane, and how ſome of them do peremptorily denie the ſtorie thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Scriptures are plain to proue, the Doctors and learned fathers plentifull to teſtifie: ſo many &amp; great are the ſignes and tokens which the Lord from time to time hath ſhewed, that Rome is Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, the Pope Antichriſt, the abhomination of deſolation, the arch-enemie of Chriſt, and that man of ſin, which lifteth himſelfe aboue all that is called God.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> Among which none ſurely is more liuely &amp; euident, and more to be weighed and conſidered, then that of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> which is ſuch a notable preſident &amp; ſingular demonſtration therof, that no man (vnleſſe wholly poſſeſſed of Satan, and a verier beaſt then euer was <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi>) will doubt or put any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence therein. This is that which is the onely eyeſore, and biting coraſiue to our aduerſaries, which pulleth downe their proud peacocks feathers, &amp; battereth their paper wals cleane to the ground. This is
<pb facs="tcp:14603:3"/>that which grieueth them to the galles, and pricketh them to the quicke, which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmeth them with horrour, &amp; drowneth them top and taile in ſhame and diſhonor. <note place="margin">Eus;eb. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi> Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati pudore &amp; adoperti co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ione diſcedunt</note>For as the ſhamefull and deteſtable end of <hi>Arrius,</hi> was ſuch a terrour and cooling card to his adherents, that they went away huſht, ouercome with ſhame, and couered with confuſion: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtrange euent of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> and her opprobrious death, is ſuch a torment and torture vnto them, that in their own conſciences they are ſtinged and accuſed, and compelled to crie: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa</hi> 1.21.</note>
                  <hi>Quomodo facta eſt meretrix vrbs fidelis? How is that faithfull Citie become a ſtrumpet? <note place="margin">Anton. Par <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>16.</hi> cap. <hi>1.7</hi>
                     </note>Antoninus</hi> the Archbiſhop of Florence, when he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened this whole ſtorie of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> was ſo aſtonied with the ſtrangeneſſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the matter, that he cried out: <hi>O altitudo ſapientia, &amp; ſcientiae Dei: quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credibilia ſunt iudicia eius!</hi> O the depth of the wiſedome and knowledge of God, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible be his iudgements!<note place="margin">A ſtorie wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, liuing in the time of king Edward the ſonne of Egelred, and Emma.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">See Marianus printed at Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil, <hi>collum.</hi> 407. <hi>ſub an. Dom.</hi> 854.</note>
                  <hi>Marianus Scotus,</hi> perceiuing what a déepe downfall and ruine this brought to the Sea of Rome, and that God would haue ſuch a matter openly knowne, to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deteſtation both of the perſon and place, writeth thus: <note place="margin">The Author corrupted.</note>
                  <hi>Propter turpitudinem roi, &amp; muliebrem ſexum, Authores Pontificij
<pb facs="tcp:14603:3"/>huius Iohannae nomen non ponunt. <hi>Both for the ſhame of the matter, and alſo for the woman kind, the Popiſh Chroniclers leaue out the name of Pope Ioane.</hi>
                  </hi> Can there be a more manifeſt token then this, both of great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of manners, and diſſoluteneſſe of life? Can there be a more infallible argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of open horror and filthineſſe, in that onely Sea aboue all others? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.15.</note>Surely, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes, &amp; all his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are done in truth and equitie. <note place="margin">A proper fig-leafe of our aduerſaries to couer Dame Ioane.</note>But our aduerſaries haue a figge-leafe to couer this ſhame, and thinke by that, to ſhift and face out the matter, and to paſſe away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible in a cloud. They flatly denie that there was euer anie Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> in Rome, yea they ſtoutly and ſturdily defend it, and ſay, that it is a fond and vaine fable, a lye, and a tale inuented of malice and ſtomach againſt them. Soft and faire, my Maiſters: your figge-leafe is drie and withered, and not worth a rotten figge, for it doth vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer your ſhame, ſhew your nakedneſſe, and bewray your trecherie and daſtardneſſe in the cauſe. <note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note>You cannot bridle the flowing Seas, nor blind the Sunne-beames: you haue as great an aduantage by the deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, as the <hi>Ebionites</hi> had by denying S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, and calling him an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata
<pb facs="tcp:14603:4"/>of the Law. But can you proue it ſo? Alas you cannot: for your owne Doctors and Proctors haue written and related it ſo plainly and pithily, that you muſt néeds (vnleſſe you clip their credits, and deface them) confeſſe it. <hi>Martinus Polonus</hi> the Popes Penitentiarie, and a Monke of the order of Ciſterce, who liued about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare of our Lord <hi>1320.</hi> hath written and repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it: <note place="margin">Iohan <hi>8.</hi> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ier vt fertur. <hi>Teſtimonies or the proofe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f Pope Ioane</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vs dicitur.</note>So hath <hi>Platina in Iohanne. <hi>8</hi> Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Enneadis <hi>9.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> Marianus Scotus: Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſius Textor in Officina: Antoninus</hi> the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Florence: <hi>Supplementum Chronico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: Faſciculus temporum,</hi> and other moe. Are all theſe lyers and tale tellers? Are the writings of all theſe men fabulous and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true? I truſt you will not ſay ſo. Then giue place vnto the truth, and kicke not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpurre: for the truth is great, and will preuaile, will ye, nill ye, it will conquer. Denie not ſuch a miraculous to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſhewing as it were in a glaſſe, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and abhomination of the Romane Church, and of the Pope thereof, the open aduerſarie of God, and the abhomination ſtanding in the holy place. Acknowledge and cenfeſſe it, and let the remembrance therof worke ſuch repentance and remorſe in you, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t you may renounce your errors, abiure your herefies, forſake the kingdome
<pb facs="tcp:14603:4"/>of darkneſſe, and ſerue the Lord in true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. How ſome of our aduerſaries go about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and ſhift the matter, by poſſibilitie of nature, ſaying, that Pope Ioane might be Hermaphroditus, that is, a man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man both in one.</head>
               <p>THe Lion is knowne by his clawes, the Leopard by his ſpots, and our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries by their peruerſe and corrupt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to defend Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> and to colour her filthineſſe and abomination withall: wherein as manie of them haue toyled and moiled not a little, ſo eſpecially hath one <hi>Cope</hi> our countriman, an earneſt Procter for the Pope and his Prelates, who wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this matter, ſaith thus:<note place="margin">Dialogo. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>47.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Neque hic ego quicquam dsco de Hermaphroditis &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>de quibus veterum librs pleni ſunt. <hi>I will here ſay nothing of ſuch perſons as be called Hermaphroditi, and are both man and woman all in one, whereof in old writers we find much mention.</hi>
                  </hi> Meaning thus in effect, that the Pope might be <hi>Hermaphroditus,</hi> an <hi>Herkinalſon,</hi> that is to ſay, a man and a woman both in one: and thinking by this meanes ſomwhat handſomly to excuſe and ſhift the matter. Gentle ſtuffe for the nonce;
<pb facs="tcp:14603:5"/>and worthie diuinitie for ſuch a Romaine courtier. What toy is there ſo vaine and ridiculous, and what excuſe ſo childiſh and friuolous, which they will not force to ſerue their turne? The Pope may be a man and a woman both in one: verie likely, for he might peraduenture waſh himſelf in the fountaine <hi>Salmacis</hi> in <hi>Caria,</hi> and be made halfe a man: or he might perchance embrace a woman as the Nymph did, finding <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maphroditus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Mercurius</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> naked, and deſire of the gods as ſhe did, that of them two might be made one bodie. Is not this Catholike Theologie, and Apuſtolike diſcipline méete for a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane champion? Is not this credible and to be iuſtified? <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orn. Agrippa de Occul. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſophia. lib. <hi>1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note>Yes no doubt, for the Pope that is a God &amp; aboue Angels, may tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe if it pleaſe him, as well as <hi>Proteus, Periclimenus, Achelous,</hi> and <hi>Metra</hi> the daughter of <hi>Eriſichtho,</hi> and may and can do greater miracles then theſe: for in his hands is heauen, hell, and purgatorie, he hath all the earth at his commaund, all the ſaints at his commandement, yea, and all the diuels too if néed be. Therefore a ſmall matter it was for him, and the leaſt miracle of a thouſand, to make himſelfe a man and a woman both in one. What cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed doctrine is this? alas what a childiſh
<pb facs="tcp:14603:5"/>and ſillie excuſe is this, to couer Dame <hi>Ioanes</hi> infamie, and to bring her to ſome credite in the world? Omiſerable &amp; phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall imaginations, of verie heathen Atheiſts &amp; Apiſtes not allowed nor main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. For ſhame, for very conſcience ſake, for the regard of the world, and for feare of Gods heauie wrath, reiect ſuch foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh dreames and ceremonies, and vphold no longer ſuch blind and vaine excuſes, in defence of that which is ſo wel and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne to the world, and which is ſuch a cleare light, and plaiue ſignification of ſacriledge, ſuperſtition and idolatry in the Romane ſea. Let not Antichriſt any longer deceiue you, nor the Romiſh Babylon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect you with her poyſoned cuppes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.13.</note> Damne not vp the ſprings of the water of life, nor breake vp puddles of your owne, ſuch as are able to hold no water, but ſerue the Lord with feare, and reioyce vnto him with reuerence; embrace his word, loue him, and put your whole truſt in him: then you ſhall be his people, and ſhéepe of his paſture, then your leafe ſhall not wither, yea and then looke whatſoeuer you ſhall do, it ſhall proſper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. How ſome ſay, that the Pope being a man, may afterwards be changed into a woman.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:14603:6"/>
               <p>GReat is the ſubtiltie, and maruellous is the craft y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sathan vſeth to drowne men in hereſie, to thruſt them headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne and perdition, and to make them obſtinately wallow and welter therein. He will prouide for them ſuch fine excuſes: he will get for them ſuch ſtarting holes and defences, that they ſhall thinke themſelues ſecure, to be in the right way, and to ſtand vpon good and firme ground, when it is far otherwiſe: yea he will leaue no meanes vnaffayed to kéepe them in his ſubiection, and to make them drunken with their owne erronious opinions. This may be perceiued in none more perſpicuouſly then in the Papiſts, and in no one thing more apparently, then in their defence of Pope <hi>Ioane,</hi> whom the diuell hath ſo bewitched, ſo blinded, and ſo wedded to their owne ſelfe willes, that to couer her deformitie, and to paint it out with ſome colour to the world, they haue ſpread themſelues againe as the heauens, and left no way vnattemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Wherefore let vs go further, and ſée more of their dealing, and more of their fetches in the matter: and let vs come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to <hi>Cope,</hi> and ſée what a good and ghoſtly Maiſter he is for his Dame <hi>Ioane.</hi> After he had ſaid, that the Pope might vs an <hi>Hermaphroditus,</hi> he reſteth not there,
<pb facs="tcp:14603:6"/>but going further, he forceth <hi>Ouids Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſis</hi> to ſerue his turne, and ſaith, that the <hi>Pope being a man, may be changed into a woman:</hi> for theſe be his words: <hi>Et ne à noſtri temporis memoria longius abeam, non ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore monumentis literarum eſſe traditum, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierum quandam nomine Aemyliam Antonio Spenſae, Ciui Eubulano nuptam, poſt duodecimum à nuptijs annum in virum tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe. Legi etiam alteram mulierem, vbi puerum peperiſſet, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem fuiſſe mutatam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But not to go farther then the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our owne time: I know that it is written that a certaine woman named Emy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, married vnto one Antonius Spenſa a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of Eubulum, ten yeares after ſhe had bene married, was turned into a man. I haue likewiſe read of another woman, that when ſhe had bene brought a bed, afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a man.</hi> Certes this is ſtrange, for a man to be turned into a woman: but all things well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered, it is nothing ſtrange at all. For the Pope hath all lawes and knowledge within his breaſt, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he be, he is holy, and immaculate, and can worke no ſmall wonders. May not he change himſelfe into ſundrie ſhapes, as well as <hi>Iupiter, Mercurie, Apollo,</hi> and other of the Gods?<note place="margin">Metam lib. <hi>3.</hi> Ponta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us.</note> May not he be changed into a woman as well as <hi>Tireſias</hi> was: or as well
<pb facs="tcp:14603:7"/>as <hi>Caietana</hi> and <hi>Aemilia</hi> into men? Yes doubtleſſe, for he is farre aboue them, and can do much more then euer they could, Therefore maiſter <hi>Copes</hi> ſurmiſe, that the Pope may be changed into a woman, is very Catholicke and ſubſtantiall, and fit for ſuch a pregnant and illuminate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. But fie for ſhame, what a ſottiſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe is this? What a vaine illuſion and Maygame? Is there no better ſhift nor ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer refuge then this? Is there no thicker cloud to ſpread ouer the matter with more likelihood? Then who ſéeth not the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Egypt? who ſées not the ſpirituall Babylon, and the madneſſe of them that commit ſpirituall fornication with her? Better it had bene, and the ſafer way by a great deale, ſimply and plainely to haue confeſſed it, then by a myracle to turne the Pope from a man into a woman, and that which is worſt of all, obſtinately to defend it. For now euery one doth ſée, that you had leifer be filthie ſtill, then leaue off your filthineſſe, and had rather (becauſe you loue your vices) <hi>Excuſare, quàm excutere.</hi> Excuſe them, then forſake them: and as many as in ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and truth do loue the Lord, do mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e for griefe, to ſee men carried ſo heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with ſuch godleſſe and retchleſſe ima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:14603:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. How they haue left cut Pope Ioanes name out of their Calendar: and how they haue hired Onuphrius Pamuinius of ſet purpoſe to face out the matter.</head>
               <p>SOme of our Aduerſaries take this <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thimeme</hi> for an inſallible argument:<note place="margin">An Enthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meme of our aduerſaries to denie Pope Ioane.</note> 
                  <hi>Dame Ioane is not regiſtred in the Calendar among the Popes: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is but a vaine fable that euer Dame Ioane was Pope in Rome.</hi> The conſequent is very ſimple, and not to be granted, becauſe it is well knowne, that the Biſhops names as well in Rome as in other places, haue vpon ſundrie occaſions bene oftentimes quite ſtricken out of the Calendar. But Dame <hi>Ioanes</hi> name (they ſay) is not in their Calendar. It may be ſo: and wherefore I pray? <hi>Martious Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> one of their owne ſworne brothers doth tell vs. <hi>Iohanna</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non ponitur in Catalogo Pontificum, tam propter muliebrem ſexum, quàm propter deformitatem facti. <hi>Pope Ioane is not reckoned in the Calendar of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Popes, as well for that ſhe was a woman, as alſo for very ſhame of the matter.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like doth <hi>Sabellicus</hi> ſet downe. <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus defunctae honor habitus: fama tenet, ob tam foeda rei memoriam. <hi>There was no honour beſtowed at her buriall: the report is, for the
<pb facs="tcp:14603:8"/>remembrance of her filthie act.</hi>
                  </hi> By this we ſée, that the name of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was not put into the Calendar of the Popes, partly becauſe ſhe was a woman, and eſpecially, becauſe ſhe was a woman of ſuch a filthie life, and vicious behauiour. Therefore this reaſon of our aduerſaries is a blind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, and of no force. But (ſay they) <note place="margin">In Scholijs in Platinam.</note>
                  <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius Pamuinius</hi> vpon <hi>Platina,</hi> hath truly and learnedly written hereof: and he that liſt to reade that diſcourſe of his, ſhall eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beléeue the whole matter to be fabulous. Truth it is, that ſuch a one indéed hath of late written hereof, and beaten his braines not a litle to helpe out this matter, but all in vaine: for he was one of the Popes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſites, hired and procured by him onely for that buſineſſe. His booke was printed in Venice, and plauſiblie accepted of his friends and wel willers: but the ſtuffe that he hath brought in there, to make the world beléeue, that there was neuer any Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> in Rome, is ſuch traſh, and ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, that it will grieue a good Chriſtian in in his heart, to reade and ſée it.</p>
               <p>This is the craft &amp; policie of the Pope, to hire and procure men to ſmooth and ſooth his matters, and to face and grace out his impieties, with many forged lies and falſe ſuppoſitions: thinking by that meanes, to
<pb facs="tcp:14603:8"/>dazel mens eyes, and to make them beléeue they be true, godly, and apoſtolicall. <note place="margin">Moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious railers and lyers.</note>This haue many popiſh Pages of late done, and eſpecially <hi>Amphilochius, Onuphrius, Surius,</hi> and <hi>Hieronimus Bolſecus,</hi> one that hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed moſt ſhamleſſe rayling, moſt vile, ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and horrible lies and cauils, with an immoderate and vnciuill bitterneſſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding from the vnſauory and vnquiet hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of his heart, againſt the godly and reuerend miniſters of the Goſpell, <hi>Caluin, Beza,</hi> with others moe. God of his mercie grant, that they may repent &amp; amend their liues, renounce their damnable errors, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their curſed ſlanders, and not aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their wits in ſuch deſperate cauſes. For, <hi>Nemo periculoſiùs peccat, quàm qui peccata defendit. <hi>No man ſinneth with more danger, then he that ſtandeth in defence of ſinne.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. What yeare of the Lord Pope Ioane liued in Rome. How long ſhe was Pope: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene what Pops ſhe was.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Herodotus.</note>XErxes the great king of Perſia, when he brought ouer his huge armie into Grecia, ſent out his letters of defiance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the great mount Athos that is in Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donis, and commanded him to ſtand ſtill, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:14603:9"/>not to ſtirre a foote, nor to worke any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, either to himſelfe, or to his army. Euen by like authoritie, and with as good diſcretion, the Pope &amp; his hirelings haue done with Dame <hi>Ioane,</hi> who being able no kind of way, to colour or cloake her ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, haue ſent out their letters and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to all Countries &amp; Regions that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly know her, commanding them not once to ſpurne or kicke againſt her, nor ſo much as to make any record or mention of her. But let them wraſtle and wrangle ſo much as they will, let them curſe and defie while they liſt, and let <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> and all the rabble rout of them do what they can, the truth thereof will neuer be forgotten: it is and will be abſolutely knowne, to the vtter confuſion of proud Antichriſt, and to the euerlaſting execration of all the popiſh and péeuiſh ſynagognes. <note place="margin">What the cauſe was, that they haue left Pope Ioane out of their Calendar.</note>For although they haue left the name of Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> out of the Calendar of the Biſhops of Rome, only for ſhame, leſt it ſhould appeare in records that a woman, and ſuch a woman had bene biſhop of Rome, or that the biſhop of Rome had bene with child: and although they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſſe to bolſter and bungle vp the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſometime with this ſhift, ſometime with that, ſometime affirmatiuely, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time negatiuely: yet ſo many Chronicles
<pb facs="tcp:14603:9"/>would not haue recorded it, nor ſo many men would haue written it, nor the world would ſo vniuerſally haue beléeued theſe things of the Pope, more then of any other, had it not bene true, credible, and veritie. For where I pray began the hiſtorie of her firſt? In Rome. From what place was it firſt publiſhed abroad into the world? Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome. What he they that haue written &amp; declared it? The truſtie friends of Rome: yes the great authenticall Doctors &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Pope, haue deſcribed &amp; auouched it, ſome liuing foure hundred yeares agoe, ſome fiue hundred, who haue euer bin counted famous fathers in Rome, and whorthy of no ſmall authoritie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence. What yeare of our Lord was Dame <hi>Ioane</hi> Pope in Rome? As they haue written, <hi>853.</hi> How long was ſhe in the Popedome? As they haue written, two yeares, one moneth, and foure dayes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt what Popes was ſhe? As they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue written, betwéene <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> and <hi>Benedict</hi> the third. Séeing then that our aduerſaries owne friends &amp; Proctors haue written and related it, and ſo plainly and expreſly ſhewed it, I maruell with what faces any of them can denie it, or go about to excuſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:14603:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. What Pope Ioanes name was, how ſhe was not borne in England, but at Mentz in Germanie, and how ſhe came to Rome, and to the Popedome.</head>
               <p>MAny there be (I know) and thoſe our owne countrimen, who thinke and beléeue Dame <hi>Ioane</hi> to be an Engliſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne. <note place="margin">The cauſe why Pope Ioane is thought to be an Engliſh woman born.</note>I can coniecture no other thing to be the cauſe hereof but report onely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the moſt part more commen then true, and eſpecially becauſe in manie au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors intreating of this matter, is found, <hi>Iohannes Anglicus,</hi> or <hi>Iohannes de Anglia,</hi> which ſéemeth vnto them to be tranſtated, <hi>Iohn an Engliſh man,</hi> or <hi>Iohn of England.</hi> Becauſe I would haue all thoſe that be not as yet truly certified &amp; reſolued herein to agrée together, and rightly to beléeue this point, I will declare vnto them the truth of the matter, according to the opinions of the beſt and moſt approued writers. <note place="margin">Why ſhe was called Ioane Engliſh.</note>She was called <hi>Ioane Engliſh,</hi> by the ſurname of her father, and borne at Mentz in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie. <hi>Martinus Polonus</hi> the Popes ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Penitentiarie, diſcourſing at large of this matter affirmeth the ſame, for thus he writeth: <hi>Iohannes Anglicus natione Magun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, ſedit annos duos, menſem vnum, dies qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor,
<pb facs="tcp:14603:10"/>&amp;c. <hi>Iohn Engliſh (ſo ſurnamed) borne at Mentz, ſate in the Romane Sea two yeares, one moneth, and foure dayes. Theodoricus Niemus</hi>
                  </hi> alſo, ſometime the Popes Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, and therefore had good cauſe to know the truth hereof, doth liuely paint out the whole matter, &amp; expreſly ſheweth the ſame. <hi>Et fuit mulier de Maguntiae nata, quae ſtuduit Athenis ſub virili habitu: &amp; in tantum profecit in artibus, vt tandem veniens Romam per bien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium in ſchola Artes liberales legerit: &amp; adeo ſufficient fuit, vt etiam Maiores &amp; Nobiles vrbis eius lectiones frequenter audiuerint. Et poſtea eligitur in Papam, &amp;c. And there was Ioane a woman, borne at Mentz, who had ſtudied at Athens in the apparell of a man, and had ſo profited in the Arts, that at laſt comming to Rome, two yeares together ſhe profeſſed the liberall ſciences in a Schoole. And her gift in teaching was ſuch, that the Elders and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Citie reſorted often to here her reade. Afterward ſhe was choſen Pope, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pope Ioane a Dutch wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note>We néed not cite anie more teſtimonies for farther proofe hereof: theſe two do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſhew that ſhe was a Dutchwoman borne, and not called <hi>Ioane Engliſh</hi> by the name of the countrey, for that ſhe was an Engliſh woman borne in England (as many imagine) but onely by the ſurname of her father. For who knoweth not that
<pb facs="tcp:14603:11"/>there are manie at this day called by the names of Scot, Iriſh, French, Welſh, Norman, Gaſcoine, Holland, and yet not borne in anie of theſe countries, but onely in England.<note place="margin">Her right name was Gilberts, but called Ioan the eight.</note> Therefore it is true, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, that Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was not borne in England but in Germanie. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome there be (whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is verie credible and ſufficient) that ſay her name was <hi>Gilberta,</hi> and called <hi>Ioan</hi> the eight: <note place="margin">Pope Ioane was a ſtudent at Athens.</note>who likewiſe affirme, that ſhe was a Dutch-woman of Mentz, and went with an Engliſh Monke out of the Abbey of Fulda to Athens, in mans apparel. Well, truth it is that ſhe was in the yong yeares of a girle brought to Athens by one that was her louer in mans apparell. There ſhe ſtudied, and profited ſo much in diuerſe ſciences, that none were found to be compared with her. <note place="margin">Women brought vp in mens apparel, and taken for men.</note>This is not ſtrange, nor much to be maruelled at: For <hi>Rauiſius Textor in Officina</hi> writeth the like of one <hi>Marina,</hi> that diſſembling what ſhe was, liued manie yeares in an Abbey as a Monke: and of <hi>Laſthenia, Axiothea,</hi> and others, that being women, came into the Schoole in mans apparell to heare <hi>Plato.</hi> The like doth manie others write of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroſyna</hi> that holy maide, that dwelt thirtie and ſixe yeares in Monkes apparell
<pb facs="tcp:14603:11"/>among Monkes, and was neuer otherwiſe taken then for a Monke.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pope Ioane came to Rome.</note>From Athens ſhe came to Rome, &amp; there profeſſed learning openly, and had great Doctors to her ſcholers, and for opinion of learning and good life by one conſent of all, was made Pope.<note place="margin">She was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pope of Rome. Her behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in that high office.</note> Being in this high and glorious ſeate, ſhe behaued her ſelfe ſo orderly, and diſcharged that ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall office ſo abſolutely, that ſhe was with child, and as ſhe went in proceſſion deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereof, &amp; ſo died.<note place="margin">A moſt liuely preſident of the whoriſh Sea.</note> Thus was the Pope of Rome, who is ſuch a parles fellow that he cannot e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, a woman with child, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in proceſſion, dead openly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtréets, and buried without anie honour or ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. God giue all Chriſtians grace by this example to beware of the Antichriſtian and Babylonicall Pope, to renounce him, and all his errors, to reiect him and all his paraſites, and to ſée the truth, and that bleſſed hope whereunto they haue bene cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſo as they may glorifie him alone, who is the true God, and alſo that ſame Ieſus Chriſt whom he ſent downe to vs from heauen: to whom with the Father, and holy Ghoſt be giuen all honour and glorie euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
